Welcome back.
잘 돌아왔어요
If you are following along with me in JupyterLab, as I hope you are, then you will need it to have
유피터랩에서 저와 함께 하고 계신다면 커피 마시는 동안 잠시 꺼두세요
gone off for a coffee break because it will have taken about 20 minutes or so to have downloaded all
모든 데이터셋을 다운로드하는 데 20분 정도 걸리거든요 하지만
of our datasets, but they will now be downloaded and lovingly crafted.
이제 정성껏 다운로드해서 다듬어질 거예요
Here they are.
여기 있네요
The automotive one is the largest with north of 900,000 data points and office.
자동차용은 가장 크고 데이터 포인트와 사무실이 900,000개 이상이죠
Uh, sorry, electronics has more than 400,000.
전자 제품은 400,000개가 넘어요
So in total.
총합이요
Let's have a look at what we've got.
뭐가 있는지 보죠
We have a grand total of just over 2.8 million data points.
총 2마리가 조금 넘어요 데이터 포인트가 8백만 개예요
That's a lot of data points.
데이터 포인트가 많네요
It's too many data points.
데이터 포인트가 너무 많아요
We don't need anything like that number for the sorts of training we're going to be doing.
우리가 할 훈련에는 그런 숫자가 필요 없어요
Um, and that means that there's an opportunity for us to hone this data set and select the data points
즉, 이 데이터셋을 연마하고 가장 가치 있는 데이터 포인트를 선택하고 가장
that are going to be most valuable for us and give us the most signal.
많은 신호를 줄 기회가 있다는 거죠
So first of all, let's take another look at the distribution of how many tokens we have.
그럼 먼저 패가 얼마나 있는지 분배하는 걸 다시 살펴보죠
This is the same chart we did last time, and it shows you that we don't ever have more than 180 tokens
지난 번과 같은 도표입니다 훈련 프롬프트에는 180개 이상의
in any of our training prompts, which is something that we specifically set out to achieve in order
토큰이 없습니다 오픈 소스 라마 모델을 잘 조정하기 위해서
to be able to fine tune well with our open source llama model next time, but also to keep costs low
이렇게 설정했습니다 또한 개척자 모델에서는 비용을 절감하기 위해서이기도
when we're dealing with frontier models.
하죠
Let's look at the prices again.
가격을 다시 보죠
This is the complete price distribution across the 2 million or so, and you'll see that it is constrained
이건 2백만 달러 정도에 걸친 전체 가격 분배입니다 보다시피 999달러
to be, uh, no more than $999.
이하로 제한돼 있죠
So it's between 1 and 999, because that's the constraint we've put in to make sure that we've got a
1과 999 사이예요 그게 제약 조건이거든요 관리 가능한 데이터 집합을
manageable data set without crazy outliers that will distort all of our, uh, training.
확보하려면요 훈련 전체를 왜곡하는 터무니없는 예외 없이요
Um, but you'll see that we still have the same problem, that the data set is very skewed to the smaller
하지만 여전히 같은 문제가 있어요 데이터 세트가 작은 숫자로 많이 편향돼
numbers.
있죠
And there's a very thin trail.
길이 아주 얇아요
Uh, and this only goes up to 300.
이건 300달러까지밖에 안 돼요
So if we go all the way up to 1000 to the, uh, to the end of our, uh, data set.
1,000까지 올릴 수 있다면 데이터 집합의 끝까지 올릴 수 있어요
There you go.
여기요
Look at that.
보세요
This is the.
여기예요
We do have, uh, data points in there which reach up to 909.49, but you can barely see them.
909까지 도달하는 데이터 포인트가 있어요 49개요, 근데 잘 안 보여요
They barely touch the, uh, the the axis.
축에 거의 닿지 않아요
Um, because the data set is so dominated by the 800,000 or so that are coming in at lower cost points.
데이터 세트가 800,000개 정도에 지배당하기 때문에 낮은 비용 포인트로 접근하는 거죠
Uh, one other thing to do is just to have a quick look at the categories.
한 가지 더 할 일은 카테고리를 빠르게 살펴보는 거예요
This nice little bar chart is showing us how many we have in each of the different categories of data
이 멋진 막대 차트는 얼마나 많은지 보여줍니다 제품의 다양한 데이터 카테고리에 각각 얼마나
of product.
있는지요
So again, automotive dominating here with 900,000.
다시 900,000점으로 자동차가 우세하네요
And you can see it's followed by tools and home improvement followed by electronics with 400,000.
그 다음은 도구와 집 꾸미기입니다 전자 제품 번호는 400,000고요
So one of the things we want to do now is do some massaging of our data so that we have a more balanced
지금 우리가 하고자 하는 것 중 하나는 데이터를 좀 더 균형 잡힌 데이터 집합을 가질 수 있도록 다듬는 겁니다
data set, because we don't want the model to be skewed, distorted towards learning more about one
왜냐하면 하나의 특정 카테고리에서 하나의 가격에 대해 더 왜곡되어 배우는 쪽으로 모델이
particular price of one particular category.
편향되는 건 원치 않으니까요
Um, we don't mind if it's if it's somewhat, uh, favors some some, like, like cheaper prices because
가격이 싼 곳을 선호해도 저희는 괜찮아요 그게
that is the reality in the world.
현실이니까요
But we don't want to go so far that it distorts or impedes our training progress.
하지만 훈련에 방해가 될 정도로 너무 멀리 가면 안 돼요
Um, so, uh, what I'm going to do now is, is, is do some selection from this data set sample from
그래서 지금 하려는 건 데이터셋 샘플을 선택하는 겁니다 데이터셋에서 선택해 더 작은
our data set to get a smaller data set that is going to have a better representation of prices and categories.
데이터셋을 확보하는 거죠 가격과 카테고리를 더 잘 나타낼 수 있도록요
And the sort of data set size I'm going for is about 400,000 data points.
제가 원하는 데이터 집합 사이즈는 약 400,000개의 데이터 포인트예요
Um, and even that's a large data set for fine tuning purposes, really doesn't need to be that big.
미세 튜닝 목적으로 큰 데이터 세트지만 그렇게 클 필요는 없어요
But I wanted to have a big juicy data set.
하지만 전 데이터 모음이 컸으면 했어요
So 400,000 is what I've gone for.
그래서 400,000달러로 정했어요
Um, and we'll talk about how I do that.
어떻게 하는지에 대해 얘기해 보죠
So first of all, I've created a dictionary called slots.
먼저 슬롯머신이라는 사전을 만들었어요
And let me tell you what this is.
이게 뭔지 말씀드리죠
And then you'll understand exactly why I've done it.
그럼 내가 왜 그랬는지 이해할 거예요
Slots is a dictionary where the key of the dictionary is every whole dollar price of a product.
슬롯머신은 사전인데 사전의 키가 제품의 모든 달러 가격이죠
So it's from $1 to $9.99 one, two, three all the way through to 999.
1달러에서 9달러로 늘었어요 99, 1, 2, 3 999까지 쭉 가세요
So there are 999, uh, keys to this dictionary.
이 사전의 열쇠는 999개예요
And the value is going to be a list of all of the products, all of the items which have that price.
값은 해당 가격이 있는 모든 제품의 목록이 되겠죠
So in the slots dictionary in slot number two will be a list of all of the items which cost $2.
슬롯 사전에 2번 슬롯에 있는 모든 항목이 2달러짜리 목록으로 나와 있어요
And so it's organizing everything into these slots.
모든 걸 이 구멍에 정리하는 거죠
It's bucketing our data set basically.
데이터 세트를 버킷으로 만드는 거죠
Um hopefully that makes total sense.
이해가 되면 좋겠네요
If not of course bring up this code.
아니면 이 코드를 불러오고요
Step through it.
통과해요
I'm using Defaultdict is a nice little thing to know about, which is basically a dictionary which will
Defaultexpt를 사용하고 있는데 기본적으로 사전이죠
if something is missing from the dictionary, it will automatically initialize it to be of whatever
사전에서 빠진 게 있으면 자동으로 초기화해 넘겨주는 형식이 뭐든
type you pass in.
돼요
It avoids you having to put a sort of if test in your code.
코드에 일종의 if 테스트를 둘 필요가 없죠
So it makes a nice, nice, elegant code.
멋지고 우아한 코드를 만들죠
All right, so here's a bit of a meaty function here, but I explain what's going on.
비트가 있는 함수가 있는데 제가 설명해 드릴게요
Amity.
아미티요
Jupyter notebook.
주피터 공책이에요
Cell.
휴대폰요
Um, I am going to go through each of these slots.
여기 있는 모든 구멍을 통과할 거예요
Each of the 999 slots.
999개의 슬롯이 있어요
And I'm going to sample from those slots a subset of the data, which I think will be a nice representative
저 슬롯에서 데이터 하위 집합을 샘플로 만들 거예요 훈련에 사용하기에 좋은 대표
sample to use for training.
샘플이 될 것 같아요
Now, some of this I've tweaked around with arbitrarily until I've gotten comfortable with the histograms
어떤 건 제가 제멋대로 변형했어요 이것 다음에 나올 조직 문자에도 익숙해질
that will follow this.
때까지요
So it's not like there's any particular special reason.
특별한 이유 같은 건 없어요
It's more of a case of trial and error and getting to a point where you feel good about the balanced
시행착오의 사례에 더 가깝죠 여러분이 생산하는 균형 잡힌 데이터셋에 대해 만족할 수 있는
data set you're producing.
지점까지 가는 거예요
And of course, I've then run it through training and satisfy myself that I'm getting higher quality
물론 훈련을 통해 스스로 만족하게 되죠 이렇게 함으로써 더
results, uh, by doing this.
좋은 결과를 얻을 수 있다고요
Um, and so what I do is I go through each of the slots in turn, and I've decided that for anything
그래서 저는 차례대로 칸을 하나씩 통과했어요 240달러 이상의
that's worth more than $240, I simply take that whole slot.
가치가 있는 물건은 칸 전체를 다 가져갔죠
I take all of those points and add them to my sample.
그 모든 점을 제 샘플에 추가해요
Um.
네
For something less than that.
적어도 less로요
I basically have some code here that samples 1200 items from that slot.
여기 코드가 있는데 샘플이 1,200개예요
So it takes that slot, and that slot might have in it several thousand.
그래서 그 구멍에 수천 개의 공간이 있을 수 있죠
I just pick 1200 from that slot, and I use a numpy method called choice, which lets you pick a certain
1200개를 골라서 선택이라는 누피 기법을 사용합니다 특정 숫자를 고를 수 있게
number from the slot.
해주는 거죠
And one of the nice things about choice is that you can pass in something called the weights, which
선택기의 장점 중 하나는 무게라는 걸 입력할 수 있다는 거예요
is telling it to give more importance to some of your items over others.
어떤 물건의 중요성을 다른 물건보다 높일 수 있다는 거죠
And uh, hopefully this comes together no surprise for the weights.
무게추가 잘 어우러졌으면 좋겠어요
What I'm saying is let's give anything that's an automotive, a weight of one, and everything else
자동차에 들어가는 모든 건 1kg이고 나머지는 5kg이라고
gets a weight of five.
가정해 보죠
And again, this was I just played around with different numbers until I got comfortable with what it
이 부분도 여러 가지로 시도해봤죠 어떤 곡이 나올지 익숙해질
was coming up with.
때까지요
And I didn't want to take it too far because we want to stay roughly true to to the the kind of data
너무 멀리 가고 싶진 않았어요 현실 세계에 있는 데이터의 유형을 대략 유지하고
we have in the real world.
싶었거든요
But we wanted to correct for some imbalances in the data set.
하지만 데이터 집합의 불균형을 바로잡고 싶었어요
So I'm not going to go line by line through explaining this.
한 줄씩 설명하진 않을 거예요
I've given you the construct, and I'm hoping you'll now look through this and satisfy yourself that
제가 구상한 걸 보고 만족하셨으면 좋겠어요 제가 말한 대로 되고 결과물이
it's doing what I say and that you like the outcome.
마음에 들면 좋겠어요
And of course, if you prefer to craft the data set a bit differently, this is your chance.
물론 데이터 세트를 약간 다르게 만들고 싶다면 지금이 기회예요 비트
Uh, it's also perfectly possible that you will be able to beat my results in terms of my model performance,
모델 성능 측면에서 제 결과를 이길 가능성도 충분히 있습니다 카테고리마다
and you may think that it would be better to to perhaps have a different weighting of the categories
다른 무게를 두거나 다른 슬롯을 선택하는 게 낫다고 생각할
or to choose differently from the slots.
수도 있죠
So you should absolutely experiment, um, and see what you come up with.
그러니 실험을 해 보고 결과를 봐야죠
But I've run this now.
하지만 지금은 제가 운영해요
It has now created a sample list, and there are 408,000 data points in that sample.
이제 샘플 리스트를 생성했고 그 샘플 안에 408,000개의 데이터 포인트가 있어요
So that's about the size that we were aiming for.
이 정도 크기로 만들 거예요
Um, and now let's see the distribution of prices.
이제 가격 분배 결과를 보죠
And that looks a lot more reasonable in terms of the distribution of prices.
가격 분배 측면에서 훨씬 합리적으로 보이죠
We've got a lot that are cheaper still, but but it's a consistent number for every price point in the
더 저렴한 제품도 많지만 저렴한 제품의 가격은 일정하게 유지돼요
And as we get to more expensive prices, there's a perfectly decent set of of data points with higher
더 비싼 가격으로 넘어가면 더 비싼 데이터 포인트가 완벽하게 갖춰져 있어요.
You'll notice this interesting effect that there are various points.
흥미로운 효과를 보실 거예요 다양한 포인트가 있죠
Uh, predictably enough, it's things that are priced $399, $499 that have a little spike in terms
예상대로 399, 499달러로 가격을 매긴 것들은 데이터 포인트가 얼마나 많은지 측면에서
of how many data points there are.
약간 상승하죠
And that's great because that reflects the real world.
현실 세계를 반영해서 좋아요
So it's good that we're going to have that in our data set.
데이터 집합에 있는 게 좋아요
I wouldn't want to to to squash that out.
그 문제를 해결하고 싶지 않아요
Um, so when we compare this histogram of prices with our earlier histogram of prices here, hopefully
이 가격 조직도표와 아까 보여드린 가격 조직도표를 비교하면 데이터에서
you immediately see the improvement we have made to the distribution of prices in our data.
가격 분배가 얼마나 개선됐는지 바로 아실 거예요
This is clearly a more it's still skewed and the real world is skewed.
현실 세계는 여전히 삐뚤어져 있어요
Um, but there's a better representation of higher priced products.
하지만 더 비싼 제품을 더 잘 보여주는 곳이 있어요
And it's going to mean that we're going to be able to learn in a high quality way and validate our sample
그러면 품질 좋은 방법으로 배울 수 있고 샘플의 유효성을 더 확인할 수 있죠
more.
그게 만족스럽지 않다면 데이터 세트를 몇 개 생성하세요
And when we get to training, you can try them both and see the impact it makes to have a well-balanced
훈련할 때 둘 다 시도해보고 균형 잡힌 데이터셋의 영향을 볼 수 있어요.
data set.
Get it
Let's also look at the categories again.
카테고리를 다시 보죠
Um, this is the categories.
주제별로 나눠요
So actually it hasn't made a ton of difference.
사실 큰 차이는 없었어요
It's slightly shifted.
약간 기울었어요
Um, we've got a bit of a better balance.
비트가 더 잘 맞거든요
Um, I didn't want to further correct it because I feel that this is, after all, somewhat reflective
더 바로잡고 싶지 않았어요 결국 이 그림은 현실을 반영한다고 생각했거든요
And so we don't want to overly distort.
너무 왜곡하면 안 돼요
There are a healthy number of automotive products on sale, more so than others.
자동차 제품을 파는 곳이 다른 곳보다 많아요
And so this this seem good enough, but it's slightly corrected some of the imbalance there.
이 정도면 괜찮은 것 같지만 불균형이 약간 수정됐어요
Perhaps another way of looking at this is looking at a pie chart.
파이 차트를 보는 다른 방법도 있을 것 같아요
Generally speaking, often pie charts are unpopular with data scientists because bar charts are better
일반적으로 파이 도표는 데이터 과학자들에게 인기가 없어요 바
for seeing quantities side by side and seeing them in a very quantitative way.
도표가 양을 나란히 보고 정량적으로 보는 데 더 좋거든요
But pie charts sometimes are useful visuals, and let's have a look at it.
파이 도표는 시각적으로 유용할 때가 있죠, 한번 볼까요?
Here is a pie chart by category, and I should obviously do a bit of work to separate out some of these
카테고리별 파이 차트가 있습니다. 이 단어들을 구분하려면 작업을 좀 해야겠지만, 어떤 느낌인지 아시겠죠.
words, but you get the idea.
비트 주세요.
Um, and it's showing you here that automotive does have the biggest the lion's share, but it's not
자동차 업계의 지분이 가장 크다는 걸 보여주지만 그렇게 압도적이진
like it's massively dominating.
않아요
And obviously a couple of these together are more than automotive.
이 두 개를 합치면 자동차 이상의 의미가 있죠
So it's perfectly reasonable.
그러니 합리적이죠
And the little guy here is appliances.
여기 작은 건 가전제품이에요
The one that we started with way back yesterday has 1% the smallest, the smallest piece of the pie.
어제 처음 시작한 건 파이에서 1%가 가장 작은 조각이에요
Uh, quite literally in this case.
이 경우엔 말 그대로요
So that is our data set curated.
이게 우리 데이터 세트 큐레이팅이에요
Uh, it was um, a bit of work, I agree.
비트 좀 썼다고 인정할게요
And I did gloss over some of the, uh, thornier, uh, pieces in there, like the sampling.
샘플링처럼 가시 돋친 부분을 광택제로 닦았어요
And I urge you to come back and look through that and evaluate it yourself and potentially craft a better
다시 와서 살펴보고 스스로 평가해서 더 나은 데이터 세트를 만들길
data set.
바라요
Uh, we're finally going to do some last analysis on it before we upload it to the hub.
허브에 업로드 하기 전에 마지막으로 분석할 거예요
And I will see you for that in the next video.
다음 영상에서 다시 만나요